Ok, Hello!
네, 안녕하십니까?
This is Byung-seung Cho from the Ubuntu Korean Community.
우분투 한국 사용자 모임에서 활동 중인 조병승입니다.
From now on, Let's get started with Ubucon Asia 2021 Lightning Talk session, 'If you need LAMP Stack, Journey to Ubuntu with WSL2'
지금부터 Ubucon Asia 2021 'If you need LAMP Stack, Journey to Ubuntu with WSL2'
What I wanted to build with Ubuntu on WSL was just a simple WordPress site.
제가 WSL에 우분투를 올려서 만들고자 했던거는, 그냥 간단한 워드프레스 사이트 한 개였어요.
I will introduce the basic stack what I used for the WordPree site, first.
이 워드프레스 사이드를 만드려고 기본 스택을 먼저 소개를 드릴게요.
First, LAMP Stack which I choosed was putting a nginx web server on Ubuntu OS,
먼저 제가 선택한 LAMP Stack 자체는 Ubuntu OS 에 웹서버 nginx를 올리고,
Maria DB for database, and PHP
데이터베이스는 Maria DB에, 그리고 이제 PHP
That was basic configuration that I selected for WordPress requirements.
이렇게 워드프레스 위에서 필요한 기본 구성은 이렇게 딱 선택을 했구요
Although I'll use it in live server,
이거를 이제 라이브에서 이렇게 서버에서 쓰겠지만
I wanted to work more comfortably locally before the deployment,
일단 서버 올리기 전에 로컬에서 먼저 좀 더 편하게 작업을 하고 싶었는데
but since I am a Windows user,
제가 이제 윈도우 사용자이다 보니 이 윈도우가 깔려있는 노트북에
'How can I make an environment closer to the server more comfortable to use on my laptop?' struck me, first.
'어떻게 하면 서버와 좀 더 근접한 환경을 편하게 쓸 수 있게 만들 수 있을까'가 이제 제가 처음에 떠올렸던 생각이었고요.
So now, Virtualbox, or VM Ware, etc.
그러다 보니 이제 뭐 Virtualbox 나 아니면 뭐 VM Ware 뭐 등등등
Now, later, I use Multi-pass together, anyway, WSL2 was most convenient for them,
이제 지금 나중에 이제 Multi-pass 도 같이 쓰긴 했지만, 이제 어쨌든 WSL2를 써서 하는게 제일 편했다.
in simple task.
간단한 작업에서는
I want to tell that point.
그 이야기를 드리고 싶습니다.
The contents coming later are not about 'How to use Ubuntu with WSL2', but
뒤에서 나올 내용은 'WSL2를 이제 우분투를 어떻게 쓰느냐'의 내용이 아니라
there will be some troubleshooting tips in my experience such as the installation.
쓰면서 잠깐잠깐 좀 많이 막혔던 설치과정이라던가 어떤 팁들이 있었거든요.
So I'm going to share it briefly.
그래서 그거를 간단하게 공유 드릴 예정입니다.
Here are two tips that you should never miss.
일단 절대 놓치지 말아야 되는 팁 2개가 있습니다.
One is that you can insert and remove files directly from Windows Explorer to Ubuntu in WSL.
하나는 윈도우 탐색기에서 WSL 안에 있는 우분투에 다이렉트로 파일을 넣고 빼고를 할 수 있다라는 것, 이거가 하나가 있고요.
This address can now be used comfortably.
이 주소가 이제 절대 이제 편하게 잘 쓸 수 있는거고요.
Next, if you just type the code, file name, and just that folder in WSL, the Visual Studio Code editor runs immediately.
그 다음이 이제 WSL 안에서 그냥 코드, 파일명, 딱 그 폴더 쳐버리면 Visual Studio Code 에디터가 바로 실행이 되거든요.
Visual Studio Code itself is installed on Windows, so you can easily change the header file or change the CSS for a while, so
Visual Studio Code 자체는 윈도우에 깔려있는 거고, 그러다 보니 간단하게 헤더파일을 바꾼다거나 CSS의 어떤 잠깐 땡겼다 줄였다 하는 것들 설정을 바로바로 할 수 있어서
these two are literally tips that are like a quick guide. So, if you know this you can easily fix it quickly for a long time.
이 두개는 말 그대로 이제 정말 간편하게 퀵 가이드 처럼 있는 팁이니니까, 이거는 아마 두고두고 알아두시면 편하게 금방금방 고칠 수 있습니다.
When trying to use WSL2, the Windows 10 version must be checked first.
WSL2를 쓰려고 할 때, 꼭 먼저 체크해 되는게 윈도우10 버전입니다.
Well, if you're using the preview version of Windows 11 right now, it doesn't matter at all.
뭐 윈도우11 지금 프리뷰 버전 쓰시거나 이럴 때에는 전혀 상관이 없고요.
However, when it's 10, you should pay attention to third line more then anyting else.
다만 10 일 때에 제일 주의할 점이 다른거 보다 이 세 번째 줄입니다.
When you check the OS build, it has the 5 then 3 or 4 digits, and they are usually correct.
OS 빌드의 버전이 보면, 앞 다섯 자리,  뒤에 이제 세 자리 또는 네 자리가 있는데요, 왠만하면 다 맞아요.
You just need to pull all latest updates.
그냥 업데이트를 다 최신으로 땡기시면 됩니다.
But this last part has to be more than 1049 now, but sometimes it's three digits.
근데 이 뒷 자리 부분이, 이제 1049라는 것 보다 이상이 돼야 되는데, 간혹 세 자리일 때가 있어요.
If these are three digits, WSL2 will never be activated even if the rest of the conditions are met.
이게 세 자리면 나머지 조건이 다 맞아도 WSL2가 절대로 활성화가 되지 않더라고요.
So, the biggest obstacle to its activation is that part, so please don't forget and take care of it.
그래서 그 활성화에 걸림돌이 제 큰 부분은 그 부분이니까 그거 잊지 말고 꼭 챙기시기 바랍니다.
Yes, in the beginning I said that we can send and receive files directly from Windows Explorer to directories in Ubuntu, but there is reverse direction way.
네, 처음에 이야기 했던 것 중에 이제 윈도우 탐색기에서 우분투의 폴더로 바로 파일을 주고받을 수 있다고 했는데요, 그 역방향도 있습니다.
It means, if you look at Ubuntu, you can enter directly from the mount directory as a Windows local drive like this.
그러니까 우분투에서 보면, 윈도우 로컬 드라이브로 바로 마운트 디렉터리에서 이렇게 바로 들어갈 수가 있는데요.
Even if you do that, it doesn't matter anyway.
그렇게 작업을 해도 충분히 다 상관은 없습니다.
However, in the initial state attached like that, chmod or chown cannot be executed anymore.
다만, 그렇게 붙어 있는 최초 상태는 이제 chmod 나 chown을 실행할 수가 없어요.
Running it doesn't change permissions or settings.
그걸 실행을 해도 고난이 바뀌거나 설정이 바뀌질 않습니다.
To change that, first, you should unmount the mounted drive itself from Ubuntu.
그거를 바꾸려면, 이제 일단 우분투에서 그 마운트 드라이브 자체를 unmount를 하고요.
Then, when remounting after unmounting is finished, you should mount it again with the metadata value and the setting value
그 다음에 unmount가 끝난 상태에서 다시 마운트를 걸 때, 메타 데이터 값이랑 그 다음에 설정 값을 같이 걸어서 이제 다시 마운트를 걸어주면
then, itself would be setted up to orchestrate configurations such as user permissions.
그게 곧, 사용자 권한이라던가 뭐 이런 것들을 바꿀 수 있게 설정이 잡히거든요.
You can it in this way, so this setting would be much more convenient than you think.
그렇게 해서 쓸 수 있으니까 이거 잡아 놓으면 생각보다 또 많이 편합니다.
There are times when it is annoying to run Windows Explorer inside Ubuntu as well.
Ubuntu 안에서 또 윈도우 탐색기 조차 실행하는데 귀찮을 때가 있어요.
Or, accessing to fold through the network can also be annoying.
혹은 폴더 자체를 또 네트워크 타고 들어오고 이런거 귀찮을 수가 있으니까.
So, it would be good to know this as well.
네, 이것도 하나로 알아 두시면 알아두시면 좋을 것 같습니다.
Then, the following may be a habit only I have.
네, 다음은 제가 또 저한테만 있는 습관일 수도 있습니다.
Originally, when I was using IaaS in AWS, Azure, or cloud like this, when server goes wrong,
원래 제가 AWS나 Azure나 이런 클라우드에서 IaaS로 쓸 때에는 그냥 한번 setup하다가 서버 값 잘못 잡았을 때
Terminated it, and created a new one, I just repeated this routine.
그냥 terminate 시켜버리고 새로히 생성하고 이걸 반복을 했었거든요.
However, I used it in WSL2 as it is, however
근데 그 버릇 그대로 이제 WSL2에서도 바로 쓰다가
when it come to 'The setting went wrong but it's annoying to revert it', its installation is simple, so
그냥 '어 설정 잘못 잡았는데 되돌리기 귀찮아' 그러면 그냥 설치 자체가 워낙 간편하니까
I just went to the MS store again and press Install Ubuntu and continue to use Ubuntu like this.
그냥 다시 MS 스토어 들어가서 우분투 설치 누르고 이렇게 계속 우분투 썼었거든요.
As I kept to use like this, I kept repeating the reinstallation.
이렇게 쓰다보니 설치 삭제를 계속 반복하게 돼요.
If you continue to reinstall 10 or 20 times, more and more,
설치 삭제를 계속 10번 20번이고 반복하다 보면
then, MS store showed me an error, even though I obviously deleted Ubuntu cleanly.
나중에는 MS 스토어가 내가 분명 우분투를 깔끔하게 지웠는데 불구하고, 이제 오류가 딱 뜹니다.
So the installation does not proceed.
그래서 설치가 진행이 안돼요.
In this case, there is a way to fix it by reboot.
이때는, 이제 뭐 재부팅을 해서 해결하는 방법도 있습니다.
But even after reboot, there are times when it doesn't work again.
근데 재부팅을 해도 나중에 또 안될 때가 생기거든요.
In that case, instead of Ubuntu, you should go to the MS Store to initialize the app data from MS Store, and now
그럴 때는 우분투가 아니라, 이제 MS 스토어에 가서 초기화를, MS 스토어에서 이제 앱 데이터를 초기화를 하면
you can install it without any problems.
이제 전혀 문제 없이 설치를 할 수 있습니다.
This is 'why can't I install it, Is WSL2 Wrong? What's wrong?' Don't get confused like this.
이게 '설치가 왜 안되지 왜 안되지? WSL2가 잘못 된거야? 뭐가 잘못 된거야?' 이렇게 혼란을 겪지 마시라고
Yes, I searched this tip for it.
네, 이런 팁을 한번 또 찾아 봤습니다.
Then, there is several things to do in your local WSL2(and also WSL1) after reboot.
그리고 이제 이 로컬, WSL2가 있는 로컬 자체를, 이건 뭐 WSL1에서도 마찬가지 인데요, 재부팅을 하면 꼭 해야되는게 있습니다.
What we're doing is,
우리가 하고 있는거는,
ah well, what I'm doing is the LAMP Stack, so
아 뭐, 제가 하고 있는거는 LAMP Stack이기 때문에
originally I thought that the status would be always in 'running', but whenever I reboot, it was always off.
이게 원래는 자동으로 항상 status가 서비스 중일 줄 알았는데, running 중일 줄 알았는데, 이제 재부팅을 하면 항상 얘가 꺼져있더라고요.
So, at that time, I always run the command and shell and just type 'wsl sudo service nginx start' in the command window to eat it right away.
그래서 그 때는 항상 커멘드, 쉘을 실행해서 그냥 바로 그냥 커멘드 창에서 'wsl sudo service nginx start' 이렇게 치면 바로 먹거든요, 명령어를.
So, after rebooting, you must always set this up to use the homepage.
그래서 재부팅을 하고 나서는 항상 이거를 꼭 올려줘야 홈페이지를 쓸 수 있다.
Eh, it might look like this.
에, 이렇게 보시면 될 것 같습니다.
If you don't do this, you're just like, 'Oh, I can't connect after a reboot, I can't go to the homepage' It is just not working, in that moments.
이렇게 안하고서 그냥 '어, 갑자기 재부팅하고나서 접속이 안되네, 홈페이지 안들어가지네?' 그냥 이게 실행이 안된겁니다.
So it's because the server isn't up, so you should check whether the server is running at that time.
그래서 서버가 안올라가 있어서 그런거니까 그때는 서버를 꼭 올려줘 있는지 확인을 한번 씩 해보시면 좋습니다.
With a series of tips, I've done my setting.
일련 팁들을 통해서, 이제 일단 세팅을 마쳤습니다.
After adjusting the settings, I was able to see the WordPress view.
세팅을 맞춰서 이제 워드프레스 사이트를, 뷰를 볼 수 있었고요.
When view is available, is it really the end now?
그 뷰가 되면 사실은 이제 정말 끝인가?
For now, It's not a matter of using WSL2 anymore, but creating a website itself is not the end, is it?
이제 WSL2를 쓰는 문제가 아니라 이제 홈페이지를 만드는 자체는 사실 끝이 아니죠? 그래서
So even after that, in fact, I have to upload more theme settings and other settings on the homepage.
그 뒤로도 이제 사실은 저는 또 어떤 테마 세팅이라던가 어떤 나머지 세팅들을 더 홈페이지에 더 올려야 돼서.
Yes, I have to start a new journey again.
네, 또 새로운 journey를 시작해야 되죠.
However, thanks to WSL2, I was unfamiliar with the various settings, but I was able to go through more famillar, so
그래도 이제 WSL2가 있어서, 이까지 되게 좀 제가 이런저런 설정들을 많이 낯설어 했었는데, 낯설지 않게 바로바로 올 수 있었고, 그래서
I was able to create a manual, and yes, I was able to come easily.
메뉴얼도 만들 수 있고, 네, 많이 변하게 올 수 있었습니다.
It's a short lightning talk, so rather than explaining this in detail,
짧은 라이트닝 토크라서, 뭐 이렇게 자세한 설명을 하기 보다
in fact, I don't know this technically in so much detail.
저도 이렇게 기술적으로 엄청 막 자세하게 알고 이런게 아니거든요?
Though, I hope the tips I picked up would be good help for you.
그래서, 그래도 이제 방금 제가 몇 개 pick한 팁이 꼭 많은 도움이 됐으면 좋겠고요.
If you have any feedback or other questions after this video, please post a question on the
혹시라도 뭐 이런거 보시고, 이 영상의 이후에 어떤 피드백이라던가 다른 질문 있으시면,
Facebook channel, or through the Korean Ubuntu users group.
그 뭐, 페이스북 채널이던 어떻게, 한국 우분투 사용자 모임을 통해서 질문을 올려주시거나 하면,
Then, I'll answer as best as I can.
뭐 저도 제가 아는건 최대한 잘 성심성의껏 답변드리도록 하겠습니다.
Yes, this concludes the Lightning Talk.
네, 이상 라이트닝 토크 마치겠습니다.
Thank you!
감사합니다.